[Music]
all right
hello everyone welcome to actin flab
live stream
number 37.2
it's february 9th
2022.
welcome to the active inference lab
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at the links here on
this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams feel
free to visually raise your physical
hand if you'd like or use any of our
emoji affordances
check out
activeinference.org to get updates on
what the lab is up to and also get more
information on how to participate or
check out this coda link if you'd like
to see our past and upcoming streams
we're here today in
stream number 37.2 it's our
third stream after the dot zero
background video and the dot one
group discussion we had on the paper
free energy a user's guide by man payne
and kirchoff from 2021
and
today we have a few things written
there's a couple sections of the paper
that we didn't get to last time
and
i'm sure everyone has
brought some interesting thoughts and of
course if you're watching live please
feel free to add any questions or
comments into the live chat because
we'll definitely have time to address
anything there
we'll start with a introduction and warm
up so
we'll say hi
mention anything that we're excited to
talk about today
something that we liked or remembered or
reviewed about the paper this past week
anything that we're wondering about and
as we just
mentioned before we began like
what does a dot two for
a guide look like
so um
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and i'm gonna
think while others are speaking and then
return to what the dot two can be and
i'll pass it to
stephen
hello i'm stephen i'm in toronto
um stephen sillett i uh
i'm doing a practice-based phd
around social topographies and how they
can be used in community development and
theater for development and uh
yeah i'm looking forward to looking at
some of the implications of how this
might be rolled out in
different types of context
i'll pass this over today
uh i'm dean i'm in british columbia at
the moment and
as with all things uh guide related i'm
always interested in how we
translate from the word
to the deed getting getting from a place
of
of information
that's curated to
actions that are also maybe curated
based on that
a bit of information and i'll pass it to
blue
sorry i lost my mute button i'm blue i'm
a research assistant or
research consultant in new mexico
transported back to my grad school days
i had like a mute button loss a time
warp all at the same time um
i'm excited to get into the sections of
the paper that we um didn't really
discuss like in particular like using
mathematics to validate empirical claims
or justify empirical claims and um
also kind of zooming out and evaluating
this work from
the perspective of a guide um and like i
think about the hitchhiker's guide and
like don't panic and like what are the
things that we really like need what are
the essential components of the fep
um and active inference that that we
need to communicate to others uh and
i'll pass it back to daniel who's going
to tell us what adoption really is
well
what it really has been
is the
far side of the bathtub
the dot zero we're kind of dropping into
the skating rink
and then
in the dot one there's an opening and we
explore and last week was an awesome
discussion we got to speak with the
first author
and now we
continue
but also
recollect some of the threads that we
opened and build inertia towards where
we
take it next and i think
there's almost
no genre
more appropriate for a dot 2 than the
guidebook like you put down in dean's
car manual metaphor like
you don't hold that up when you're
driving and so
papers similarly they engage our regime
of attention
transiently
you're not supposed to only be looking
at the paper so we're going to put this
paper down
we're going to end this video eventually
and then what will be left with us how
will our generative model
have been updated
so that our policy selections are
different whether they're mental action
policies
related to attention
or metacognition or whether they're
physical
action policies
so
i guess it relates to that
quintessential
dot two question
of moving from the word of the paper
that we're
engaging in
in our discussions
to the deeds and what are those
deeds
and then
it's almost like this is an
action-oriented framing
of
a dot two or of just what we're up to
today
and then there's
this
asynchronous or not temporally binding
element of
which is raised by the paper though of
what are the essential components
of fep and active and also the
differentiation perhaps between the
conceptual and the pedagogical
like
are the pieces
that are the minimal
kernel of fep and active
is that where we is that page one
on the guide
how does education
which is going to be the trajectory of a
learner
relate to
the theoretical apparatus which is kind
of like a a building or some sort of
structure that doesn't necessarily have
a trajectory like format
so maybe just to return to this question
though of the word and the deed
in the dot one
we heard about
what the target audience was from the
author's perspective
for this paper
which was um it's a special issue um
it's a topical collection
called the free energy principle
from
biology to cognition
and we heard a little bit about how the
editor
made a request
of the authors to
write this
special piece
and they also summarized it in their
last aim
we aim to increase
philosophical understanding
of active inference
so that it may be more readily evaluated
so within the philosophical domain
so that it can be evaluated
but
what other domains
or
ideas are important here then what are
these
actions so philosophers might be
interested in reading this so that they
can better
philosophically evaluate but
what are the
idea to deed
pipelines that we're interested in or
opening up here steven and then anyone
else
one of the aspects that
this this paper talks about is
how much things can be screened off how
much
it gives us latitude to separate out
realistic empirical interpretations from
um the modeling
of
and
i think that's a feature they also talk
about and i'll be interested in what
others think about this but they talk
about the markov blanket is giving this
opportunity to screen
or screen out what's inside and outside
and
i wonder how
this idea of screening because screens
are not the same as a wall it's not it's
not walling off
but as come up on the twitter
conversation with casper hesp this week
this idea of leakage like if i have a
screen
i've got a blind here as i described
earlier and there's some leakage through
the blind right
um but is even that idea of screening
off
a little bit passive
i'm curious about that a little bit dead
anyway
yeah if there weren't
statistical dependencies between
internal and external states
like if there were two states that
were just not even there was no path
from here to there
there wouldn't even be able to be
blanket states partitioned out
so internal and external states are
conditionally independent
upon the blanket states
using the narrow pearl 1988 sense of
markov blanket
but
there is a channel there is a path
from the internal to the external state
again otherwise they wouldn't even be
part of the same click in that part of
the bayesian graph
um
and then also yes stephen
yeah so that this this this click this
question of how much
we
need to
find purchase through
that blanket
and the screening off and how much we
can get away with
more broadly thinking about the free
energy principle and inference and
how that can be stepped up and down
depending on
where we are in terms of empiricism and
trying to make claims
um themes to feature a lot in this paper
um and i'm i'm i'm sensing that
because they're they're sort of arguing
in a way that as long as you can get
functional
functional correlations
then
how you get at them
be that approximate
isn't necessarily
about it being the real world that gives
you it
there may be different ways to arrive at
something
that's approximately
youthful and i think that speaks the
dynamical systems over traditional
systems in the sense that
i can have
a system which isn't the real system but
if my system flips or the regime shifts
in similar ways to the target
as opposed to it actually being it and
and and having the right types of values
in it
in itself it's more about what's the
what's the way that i start to see
my uncertainties flip from one belief to
another
if the if the way the belief updating
happens
is still approximately useful enough
for something to happen
that's viable
then that is
still okay
and i'm wondering if that isn't possible
in normal systems work which isn't
dynamical systems work
let's
look at the
order and kind of trace the trails of
the authors so in the early example
we had just the case of perceptual
inference which was first introduced in
the exact base context and then we moved
into the variational base
caprents
and we had w
world states
unobserved
that's the actual temperature in the
room
x observed data that's the reading on
the thermometer
so this is the
um simplest
bayesian latent or hidden state model
so
is there a markov blanket here
asking for a friend
[Laughter]
no because there's only two notes so
there cannot be
a partitioning between internal and
external states conditioned on a third
note they're sort of um it's kind of
like the minimum two but now we're
taking to like minimum three you can't
have a blanket an intervening or an
intermediating or a state which makes
two others conditionally independent
unless you have three three's a crowd
three's a party
now
in figure three
there's the basic model of action so we
still have the same definitions and
meanings of w
unobserved world states
and x observations those observations
are now being passed to the agent
and indeed they were implicitly being
passed to the agent above
if there would have been a third node
agent there
it could have been said that the x was a
markov blanket but as it's exactly
written there isn't
now
here
what are the blanketing states
x and z
if you
are conditioning upon x and z it makes w
and the agents conditionally independent
and this is sort of presaging the
fristen partition on the markov blanket
which is to split up the notion of the
total set
of intermediating or
conditionally independent ising states
no
markov to pearl epoch
and showing them in a way that's
partitioned into incoming from the
asians perspective
statistical dependencies which can be
interpreted as sensory states or the
observation of model data
and then outgoing statistical
dependencies z
z action you select
and then those can have some influence
on
world states
yes stephen
you know you say outgoing statistical
dependencies and that's also interesting
because it's is it at some point the
outgoing
cannot
be statistical alone because you you
don't have the same kind of
information
availability so it tends to be more
using energy and
sort of least action type approaches so
that would be
i'm sort of preempting that but that's
where it starts to split out later but
they they don't get bogged down in that
at this stage they they
keep it all in the sort of bayesian
environment
not exactly sure what you mean since
these arrows represent not mechanistic
or
causal influence but just statistical
dependencies in the
graph
yeah i was thinking more when that
becomes action
uh when it's then translated to be
action so then
um
rather than sensory which has much more
sort of informational
content
action can be seen as being more
about
what is more energy efficient
or starts to look at more
the shape of
the way that action happens
i'm wondering whether that is
uh
needed to be concerned about
if it were a software agent
then
these are both informational
really
and no matter what type of agent we're
modeling
it's still just a statistical dependence
okay
then
you brought up questions about energy
expenditure
during action and that's one of the
pieces that
is sometimes
challenging to parse out
which is like
um
first looking at variational free energy
minimization
so this is on the perceptual side we're
looking at the instantaneous fitting of
a variational model
of ongoing sensory information
given the priors
that doesn't mean that
for for example an organism it's the
lowest energy possible interpretation
of the sensory data
and then when we
bring action into the picture and look
at expected free energy
neither does this mean
that the z that is selected is the
laziest
it just means that this g is being
minimized
and
so it's not the gibbs free energy or the
calories that are being minimized it's
something informational that has to do
with model fitting
yes go for it yeah now that that that
definitely makes sense um and one thing
carl fristan mentioned in um the
symposium we did is there's there's kind
of two boundaries there's kind of two
boundaries happening in terms of
markovian boundaries there's one coming
in and there's one going out
and the blankets kind of got both of
those
boundaries
happening so like you said yeah it's
it's
the way that then the inference happens
to know what actions to take
is different but the way that
information
is
established
is for sure different
going through each of those as i mean as
it is with every mode
of sensory data that comes in because it
could be vision it could be here and it
could be
a kinesthetic
so you've got different types of input
and you've got different types of output
but there
and in this diagram at the moment it's
keeping both of those there's no idea of
leakage or
of those questions about how things leak
across between it's like there's there's
two distinct
blows going on
but that and it simplifies in that sense
yes
um
[Music]
we've seen other
topologies of perception cognition in
action like an edge connecting sense and
action states
or
an arrow that's
having a statistical dependency the
other way okay but just to return here
yes dean go for it
this is a question for everybody here so
stephen the first author
talked about the fact that sort of the
back story of this whole guide thing was
to
and i'm putting words into it but i want
to keep it reasonably short i talked too
much last week
he basically wanted to be able to remove
some of the impediments and he pointed
directly at some of the math
that acted as a maybe a kind of a
a bridge too far
and so he wanted to make that a simpler
um
maybe something that's more
user-friendly
and therefore something that people will
take up or adopt and when you're putting
on this um
when you're putting up this slide here
now daniel
i don't know
whether i know it eventually will be
translated into the math formalisms you
just point you had them up a minute ago
but i'm not really sure whether the
evaluation aspect that philosophers
are going to
then decide whether something is worthy
of their
their continued attention or not i'm not
sure if that i don't
how does this critical path critical and
evaluation being related in this context
how does this
minimize or reduce
the impediment nature of what the math
is like if we're gonna we're gonna guide
somebody through this and their and
their one of their hopes is to be able
to say okay well i'm not just
making this stuff up there's actually
some
some way of being able to formalize this
how does that
through this kind of
first step
become
become easier i guess in terms of what
the actual formula says because i know
that when i first actually touched on
the formulas myself
it didn't go back to a critical path
like there was no real physical example
i could find in the world and i think
maybe that's what helped me understand
that maybe
this this thinking or this ability to
think statistically sorry
to think statistically maybe that
requires as carl also said
our ability to
do the math we have to be able to do the
math and the math doesn't get simple so
i'm wondering what people think about
that
okay stephen if you have a direct
response yeah yeah well i think that um
in some ways this goes back to a little
bit before where the math was it helps
us see why the math was put in at
certain points
by going to even a stage earlier so i
think there is some use in that because
i think like you say
um
there is a slight inflation in the way
that the process theory then gets
interpreted and if it's already locked
in too much in what's given to us with
all the math it's like well where did
that math come from and and then that
starts to get us involved in some of
these earlier questions because what's
interesting here is
see the blanket
i think of the blanket often as
as a method for transfer
it's a mode for transfer just a bit like
lithographic blankets transfer from an
analog roller to a blanket roller um to
a printed image and to the paper it's
transferring now it's it also does mean
that
there's no direct contact between paper
and
um
paper and printing plate right
so it's screened off as well but it
depends which way it's gone at you know
um
and
in this case here with these red circles
it's useful to think about okay well
there's there's something that's been
inferred
from the world
um
but that influence isn't directly
accessible it's
it's not
that observed data
isn't coming in as
data it's coming in as um
[Music]
what's inferred to be
about what's out there
which isn't the same as a signal
so it's like how much is the agent
able to have the environment transfer
something onto them and transfer
something onto the environment and how
much are they screened off from
the environment how much is the
environment screened off from them i
suppose that's
that's something that relates to that
hey thanks
so
dean
you asked how does the yes you wanna go
for it first
no go ahead and then i'll just follow up
both you and stephen okay so you asked
how does the critical path the linear
pedagogical path that is traced by this
version of this guide
reduce the actual or perceived
impediments
in an audience specific or in a general
sense
so it definitely helps us see where math
could or should or does or will enter
the picture
i think it sets up an aboutness of the
math like
what is perception about
this is a graphical interpretation
graphical meaning visual but also
like a network
bayesian graph
and so
if you're concerned with a different
connectedness
of terms
this is not the math you're looking for
but on the perception side if this is
kind of how you're setting up
the template for what you're wondering
about like what's out there that's what
this first image shows with wnx
what's out there
and how do i act or how does an agent
act that's the aboutness
which is not unique to active inference
that's control theory cybernetics etc
the stepwise guide element
it reminds me i hope it's not unrelated
in high school cross country
the coach would say something like well
the race is going to start and you gotta
get out there fast and then it's the
middle is the part where you need to be
running and going hard then at the end
you gotta push it and finish and run
hard and everything
and i was like
you could have just said run the whole
time was it not the same thing as saying
run at the beginning middle and end and
so
but
run really hard during the whole race
i don't know coach
a whole race is a long time to run
here by breaking it into really
specific
stepwise changes to the math like a
piecewise defined function
there's an opportunity to pace and lead
a learner
and then
to
accumulate or pause
for
divergence or prediction error that
they're experiencing
like maybe before this first train stop
someone has a question about that or
maybe
just graphically when action enters the
picture somebody has a question about
that
now we could be talking about
equations symbolic equations that
describe the w to x relationship
or the agent to z to w relationship and
then this paper is going to propose just
one symbolic expression or several
symbolic expressions
that today we call octave inference
approach to
addressing that question but it builds
up the aboutness in a stepwise way
that even though
it is conceptually no different than
just saying here's the action perception
loop and the equations which is pretty
much what every fap paper does but by
starting somewhere a lot more atomic it
allows the stepwise addition of the math
in a way that's incremental rather than
like here's the apparatus
and that leaves much of it implied dean
yeah and i wouldn't disagree with
anything you're saying there because i
but i do think that there's a not too
subtle difference between step wise
and then the kind of step function the
leaving of the critical path
and now
seeing
seeing a set of mathematical formalisms
around a statistical distribution and
i'm just wondering
how that transition occurs because it
doesn't seem like there's a natural ramp
from following
something clockwise or counterclockwise
to being able to change things into
um
alphanumeric
ratios
which is essentially what the statistic
when the when it's written out
statistically what that does right the
sum and the and the and the ratio so
if if if the impediment was
some of the um
non-frequent math
and i'm not i'm not critiquing in any
way what steven's
written out here in his guide but
it seems like there's
still some assumption on the author's
author's plural part
that
you will be able to take enough from
this critical path representation to see
what it looks like when you're
over fitting like i like that there was
a lot of explanation of what overfitting
is and then there was plunk and here's
the formula that that
that that um
that overfitting
um
looks like in in mathematical form so
it's kind of a big assumption that the
the person who's reading this is going
to be able to make that leap go from
this level of walking clockwise or
counterclockwise to now suddenly being
able to
understand what all of those different
symbols in that formula means
i'm not i'm not saying it can't be done
but i'm just wondering how
how as people who are trying to lay out
something in a kind of step step
progression
how they
assume that they can just sort of put
holds into that big wall and people
still don't have a fear of heights
right like it's still it's still better
than not having a ladder
but
but it doesn't mean i want to go up 40
feet without safety right just because
it's there and i kind of see that in
terms of how the transition works
between
this kind of sim this this
um this form of representation and then
what the representation looks like in
the math that's a big leap i think for a
lot of people
thanks dean stephen
yeah and one i suppose one danger that's
always present when
naming things is
and they then move into this with with
the predictive processing
um
discussion you know how much can you
name things as being data
in these contexts so it becomes
statistical but like you say um
the
there is effectively
information coming in
but
data in some ways
may be a bit of a tricky word to use
because data kind of
implies an in
inherent um
representational nature and they talk
about this in the paper a little bit of
that tension between something that's in
is coherent enough and can be
represented and something where you
can't ever quite get at that the
inference the predictive processing
has to then
leverage something like generative
models using the body etcetera to even
get at the uh
that that that that um
to allow that arrow to be
something in a much more fuzzy way you
know
um and uh so there was always that risk
of
leading people astray even at this early
stage
so a few
comments there
gene you asked like how do we get from
this graphical layout so we've taken the
first
bite
which is this is
roughly the correct topology for
thinking about problems of perceptual
inference and action inference
that
is
if someone re
imagines this
amazing but this is just
the approach to perception cognition and
action and impact
that is a common kernel of a phrasing
now
let's just
think about it as an example rather than
just the um abstraction let's just say
that we're interested in
listening to a cat
and then inferring what its location is
so we're only talking about this simpler
w and x connection
first
so
here's what the empirical data are
four two one and three
you could have a model of decision
making on x that just says the cat is
always in the kitchen
just i don't care i'm okay with being
wrong the cat's in the kitchen
um or someone could say the cat's always
in the bedroom or i flip a coin
or i go with what
some other person told me like there's
many ways to make a decision
about world states conditioned on data
one
principled approach
which they right here
one famous method for solving this
problem bayesian conditionalization
so that's the question which is framed
normatively here about one what one
ought to do
is
integrate their beliefs
which can be empirically grounded that's
parametric empirical base
upon incoming data
so first
in this case the next little tiny step
is
we can use bayes theorem
to look at inference on external states
given incoming data
again if someone disagrees with using a
bayesian approach an exact basing
approach
that's the time to speak their piece
this is a very
simple
example with like kind of the minimum
two by two matrix if it was any
thinner of a model on any dimension like
if there was only a kitchen
then the question of location inference
would be trivial it's in the kitchen
if there was only one sound
equally it would be um a trivial problem
because the sound would then be
uninformative from an information theory
perspective which they're not bringing
up here yet
about location
then the next tiny step and then dean is
to go from the exact bayesian approach
the parametric bayesian approach
to
variational caprents which is
imagine that this was not just two by
two table but there was
a higher dimensional state space of
observations
and so it's not going to be possible to
just look at this in a spreadsheet or on
a piece of paper
but it's actually
a large model
and so we need
tractable heuristics
and so that is the next tiny step from
now we're going to take not just a
principled approach to treating the w to
x relationship
bayesian perceptual inference but we're
gonna go beyond that and ask what's a
tractable and reasonable approximation
variational inference
there's other
situations where maybe there's another
tractable approach like mcmc
markov chain monte carlo that's another
approach
which we've talked about in other cases
that's the pointillism sampling based
approach it works really well for
certain problems it doesn't work as well
for other problems and so that's the
next little tiny step we're going to go
from this setup of perception to using
bayes theorem you could do otherwise and
then from using exact or parametric
empirical base to using variational
bayesian approaches and again you could
do otherwise dean and then steven
yeah and again all i all i'm i think i'm
pointing out is that i
for some it isn't a tiny little step
but i don't think it's a ramp going from
one version of representation
to foursquare version of representation
to formulaic
version of representation i think for
people who see the math maybe as an
impediment
to their further continuation
of using the
the potential of the
the free energy
principle maybe they aren't such small
steps they certainly aren't ramps
in terms of how we interpret each of
those three particular ways of
representing information there's no ramp
there's actually an actual transition
moving from from
what you've got on the screen now to the
60 40 50 50
way of being able to interpret that way
of representing the information
to the one that has an equal sign
they're very very different right like i
mean i understand the relativity piece
and all the and i i see that carrying
throughout this is what relatively
relativity looks like this way and then
this way and then this way but i think
i think the struggle for people who are
putting guides together is the
assumption that what's little for you
is little for me
it isn't always that way now i'm not i
don't know if we can fix in that here in
these labs but
i don't think it's something that we
should assume
is necessarily once one small step for
humankind
because i think the reason why the
authors were asked to
put two years worth of work in this in
the first place
was because the math is acting as an
impediment now do you start with the
math because i agreed with stephen last
week when he said this is the direction
we took we decided to slow
things down not simplify
but slow things down so i really
appreciate why they've done what they've
done but if they
knew going in that they're going to have
to go slow
then they're probably going to see
whether or not that bump
as we change representations
is actually
relatable to the previous
version or form that the relationship
was
was presented as
and i don't know that people necessarily
do like
blue is going to have to have say on
this too but she mentioned the
arbitrariness
of something that doesn't update
right and so it doesn't retain its form
and should we just assume that we all
saw
the the morphology in the same way it's
it's
it's tricky uh i'm just gonna leave that
that tricky because i'm not sure
anybody that's putting a guy together
necessarily has the
the perfect way of being able to deliver
it
okay thanks blue and then see
so something that that i think is
interesting is the mathematical
um
interpretations have like philosophical
underpinnings almost or maybe it's the
other way around so
when you're looking at like for example
this
difference between a probability
distribution and a preference
distribution like if the cat
is in the kitchen 75 of the time you can
just assume there's like the underlying
assumption that it prefers to be in the
kitchen
most of the time right like so
because that's where the food is or or
whatever so
and similarly like in homeostasis if i'm
at 37 degrees celsius that's my
temperature
if i'm there 95 of the time
you can assume that i have a preference
to have a body temperature of 37 degrees
celsius i think that there's that
underlying connection but but it gets
really complicated when you try to
extrapolate to something like cognition
there's like i prefer to
be rich i prefer to have 90 of the money
in the world for example like you can
say like i want all the money like you
think about something like that but then
there are so many complicated like do i
really want all the money no because
then everyone else would be homeless and
impoverished should be horrible right
like so you don't really want all the
money like there's
and and then if i say if i prefer to be
rich but i'm stuck in an impoverished
situation you can assume that there's
like a learning gap between how do i
earn money
and
being in the face where i don't have any
money like i don't know how to have
money like there's a knowledge level so
when you when you bring cognition into
it and like you ask people like what
their preferences are like i prefer to
live by the beach but i live in new
mexico i mean we have lots of beach but
no water so so there's like you know
there's there's
i i don't know there there's the
preferences and then the probability but
but
is there some kind of like cognitive
dissonance like you think we think what
our preferences are
are maybe not where our probability
distributions are like i prefer to be by
the beach but ninety percent of the time
i prefer to be by the ocean but ninety
percent of the time you find me in the
desert that's that there's
like there's some cognitive dissonance
going on there and so i think that the
mathematical
interpretations have a lot of
philosophical
implications
that maybe you know we need to think
about more like when is a preference
distribution and a probability
difference
distribution different and why are they
different like what is going on when the
preferences are not the probabilities
thanks blue
yes this will take us soon to the tale
of three piece stephen first
yeah very good points there um
when you said daniel there about the
exact base on the world um
it goes into the so
it goes into the variational base which
in some ways as it starts to hit the
markov blanket and start to give
time steps as it starts to go through
into the generative model
you then got and as was useful from our
um
again the symposium with carl pristin he
talked about you know the starting point
often for active infrastructure is the
generative model you know how do you get
at the generative model so the general
rule is
that in some ways this exact base is
almost needed in the modeling sense to
give you what we think we know the world
is when we're setting up our
model or our experiment of people
doing
something where we're going to see what
the results are so it's like
the agent can't know
what w is they can't know what the exact
base is but like with the cat experiment
sorry the cat matrix there okay we we
could arbitrary put one in
that we kind of can say we know as
objective observers it's going through
goes the agent and then the agent does
something okay
and and as blue said sometimes that
that what they do
isn't only in response to what's coming
in which is quite often not it's not
just can i i've seen food can i eat food
as much food as possible does this well
what's the consequence of my actions
going forward maybe a lot of times we
then start to get into this higher
dimensional stuff
where
the circle that you put in there going
into w there's that red circle on the
left
which so it goes into the w
is what
is really of concern
you know the humanities around what's
what's that about
right
and
a lot normally the generative model work
that is done in active inferences is the
circle on the right hand side i how do
we predict the way beliefs are being
updated and what's the way the beliefs
because it's normally coming in that
direction
because you can sort of control
you can do an exact base there's the one
place you can theoretically set your
experiment with an exact base is w
it's kind of hard to put exact base on
an agent unless of course it's a robot
potentially
um
so i think there's something quite
interesting there
about um
how much is this
um and it's a practical instrumental
tool right how much is this about
the way that modeling happens
and how much and and the math to make
that happen and the philosophies to make
that and how much then is this broader
and it may be that it gets recapitulated
depending on which
parts we simplify or allow to be more
complex or want to get a purchase on
out of those
circles and maybe you just explain why
you put the circles where you put them
just to see if i'm
getting your um
your rationale but i think that was kind
of useful to put them in
i'm just highlighting the directedness
of the statistical dependence
this circle
of action policy influencing unobserved
states
we've seen it in a partially observable
markov decision process as where
that's
b
w changing through time is b
that's how hidden states change through
time
state one state at time one state at
time two
then
z
influences
here
in this
simple only four nodes so if you only
get four nodes
you draw the dependency that way
like my action to change the thermostat
in the future will change the
temperature
when we can unpack it a little bit more
and move it from this sort of minimal
cybernetics or control framing
into
some of the little bit more built out
models we've looked at that is where
policy selection
influences b and so yes there's enormous
concern over how our actions influence
things that we can't directly observe
save for
by proxied information incoming back to
us
and that is not a unique problem to
active inference dean and then it's even
i think i'm going to circle back to what
blue is saying because i think she's hit
on something really critical
the oneness of this i think is what
i won't say was the was the thing that
carl started on when he
took his first knees and steps into
trying to
put something that we can we can hold on
to something
that we can look at philosophically and
mathematically i don't know if he was
thinking about oneness
at that point when he started down that
path but i think
the more we talk about it the more we we
realize that
as a for example in in a guide use
i think a person who reads
stephen and the other author's work
have two questions the first one is
my use of time the number of minutes i
have to
commit to reading the guide
before i can then say whether or not
certain impediments have been removed
well at the same time and this is what i
think active inference does
it also allows us to invert that first
accounting of what we are doing with our
time
invert it from use of time
to
time of use like
so if i do commit
to reading this guide
what's the shelf life of that like how
long am i going to be able to take the
my takeaways and actually be able to
apply them to different concepts
and then there's a fleshing it out part
which i think steven's kind of talking
to which is
so
when we take all of this information and
we embody it what does that feel like
what is that what does that read out in
terms of our behaviors
etc our reactions our responses
so i think ultimately if we're looking
at the oneness of this we have to start
talking about heuristics and steven
specifically spoke about that he said i
wasn't i think i'm paraphrasing him but
i think he said
we were concerned about whether starting
with simple
doesn't also have a cost we know that it
has a benefit because it doesn't
overwhelm people
but if if we are going to look at simple
rules like heuristics does that all also
have a cost now he didn't answer that i
was just re-watching the 37-1 before we
came on today but i think that's
something here that blue has now touched
on
and i think stephen is touching on as
well if we're going to put a guide
together
when did the when did the rules fall out
do we assume that they fall out just by
picking the guide up
or do they are they something that that
the breeder or the user manufactures
after having the experience
that oneness i think is what this act of
inference stuff
is touching on and and
and it's in some cases it feels pretty
ready arbitrary it's hard to tell
the when of
the heuristic do i start with the rule
is my prior my priority or am i really
trying to update and i'm trying to come
up with something that really applies
at some point in the future that i
haven't arrived at yet
and i know that sounds
kind of not answering anything
but
even even with the statistics it's hard
to figure out what each agent is going
to do
depending upon what their bias is so
they want to start with the rule or they
want to develop one as they go along
and as
the bacillus axilis
in 34 axos bacterium
showed exact base doesn't mean you get
it exactly right
it means you're following a process and
with maladaptive priors
even accurate information coming in can
result in a maladaptive decision making
so this is not
panglossian or polyanish
just because there's an approach
doesn't mean that it succeeds
perfect right yeah um so steven then
blue
yeah so two points that sort of speak to
that
well i'll say the second one first
because it was in mind is
when we are when we see the modeling we
often see say we talk about the bacillus
or we see the way that modelling happens
high order agents such as humans
tend to find that the
the w is fixed as a like the the cat is
either purring
or it's it's meowing it's in the kitchen
this is an exact always in the bedroom
right
so it's it's a kind of defined
exact base kind of context and then that
allows the
the other parts to kind of
still find some very interesting and
tractable useful
trends right so
as it goes through
now when it goes then the other way is
okay how do you get into something which
is an exact base and you tend to see it
turn into the swarming of
of voxels
those small
you know um
lorenz attractors or bacillus so very
very very simple
a gentle
um
[Music]
scenarios with very little
degrees of freedom because
and this is in a way trying to address
that challenge of well you know what if
you don't know if it's in the kitchen of
the bedroom it's in the doorway
and it's it's wandering around and
there's the time
the time in between
getting sensory information
and
my the action
is um you know isn't in step there's a
lot more bleed out you know
and that becomes this kind of how much
is the temporal i saw this word from
from casper has leakage
um because there's a leakage out of that
sensory
um in sensory i don't want to use the
word input but the statistical
dependencies coming in and the
statistical dependency is going out
there's a leakage going on
um
uh which makes the modeling kind of
challenging though at some point it
becomes okay well it's overwhelming
right the the um we might
philosophically say
somehow we were able to do something
like that and and our biology has
enabled us to overcome that challenge
but to actually put it into a
model like the one on the right top
right there it starts to become and in a
way maybe that's where effect comes in
as maybe okay that
that may be also true for us that's why
we need something like affect
to hold together this sort of fuzzier
kind of
knowing which can't be resolved in that
such a solid way so that's the first
piece the second piece very quickly is
you put the you know the the these um
the the red circle that you put next the
x there um
so in some ways
that that is what's
like while it's sort of we're inferring
what we're really doing is we're
inferring
[Music]
we're either inferring the circle there
that comes in to the x or maybe
and that's assuming what the arrow
that's going into the agent is is what's
coming out of x
or is coming from the x
so that's in a way
the edge isn't it that's the kind of
boundary
that's being the beliefs when you say b
the b is about that
not strictly about w
there's a belief distribution on w and x
w is latent modeled unobserved states
and x is modeled empirical observed
all states
okay blue
so just to kind of riff off of what both
of you guys were saying maybe this is
tangential but but when you talked about
leakage
um it reminds me of like the information
partitioning that we discussed with
majeed benny and how there kind of
always has to be some kind of leakage
like if you have a complete information
partitioning
um
you're actually like
in a in a vacuum or a bubble like you're
you're existing there has to be some
kind of leakage across the partition all
the time um
like and i've i've come to realize this
like we have to be sharing information
with people that are you know how do we
form a markup blanket how do the four of
us come together and form this live
stream today right like we're sharing
information even though there's a markup
blanket that exists between us and for
some of us it's thicker and thinner like
daniel and i will be often like doing
the same thing at the same time like
like even like you know separately um
just because we we work together so much
but um
this leakage is there and then it also
made me think about the maladaptive um
behavior that daniel was mentioning and
so when you have this
like we always wonder what is the cause
of this maladaptive behavior and this is
something that we were discussing maybe
a couple weeks ago with jason you know
that what is the explanation for
maladaptive behavior and it always makes
me think about the scale right like in
the situations that are utilitarian
like you know maybe someone sacrifices
themself
for you know they jump in front of a
train to stop the train to save the 300
people that are on the train and so
there's the maladaptive um decisions do
occur but but perhaps it's at like a
societal scale or you know like
in a body you know one piece will die
off to save another piece like even in
the brain
um like the formation of like the glial
scar i think of that like which it's
like essentially like an it puts a hole
in your brain but it's to protect the
rest of the brain from the cell death
that's happening in that in that center
hole
and so you know it's it's there there is
this information leakage and and even
maladaptive behavior
um that i think are are scale
dependent skill friendly
thanks blue um dean and then we'll move
to another section
cool
yeah
i i don't know if we're at an inflection
point with this but i i do want to bring
this up again i i think that
the leakage speaks to another metaphor
that i've brought up way too many times
last week which is a and the in the
point zero which i think there is a
filtering piece to this
i mean this morning i put the
raspberries in the sieve and i assumed
the raspberries would stay and the water
would pass through
and there were parts that i didn't need
like i wasn't trying to make raspberry
water i just wanted to eat the
raspberries and i think that if we
understand that there's two a minimum of
two aspects to when we're talking about
active inference i think we do ourselves
a favor
and i think we do ourselves a favor for
writing guidebooks about active
inference and free energy so i think i
think the guidebook for the guidebook
if there was if there were if there were
some pillars that we could put a
guidebook on he would be my suggestions
first of all there is going to be
because we have a markup blanket we have
a separation
that differentiation and that
integration
are going to be inherent and however we
observe something and then respond to it
second thing that i would suggest is
there's a certain blind spot removal
piece to this
and i mean that in the in the context of
say something like change blindness
because of over attending or under
attending where he talked about
overfitting or failing to explain
that change blindness
now becoming a greater awareness
availability
because we don't necessarily have to
lock in prematurely or wait too long
there's kind of a sweet spot that active
inference is is trying to say exists
it's not perfect
but it's it's better than not having a
sweet spot third thing i would say is
if we're ignoring the foraging aspect of
this
if we expect that the framework is going
to be
another frozen meal then you're going to
get the quality of a frozen meal if
you're willing to forage around the
perimeter of the store
you're going to come away with a whole
different experience it's more time
consuming but in the end it's like
learning to fish
it's it's it's a whole different way of
trying to process
those uncertainties
right
so
i think at the end of the day what pops
out or when
when we decide that we can actually say
somebody's using active inference
whereas before they weren't
i think what they do is they come up
with a a new sense of what rules
which are being updated which are being
modified which are being iterated and
sometimes even being extrapolated
we have to really focus on what that
means under particular circumstances
as we move from place to place
so again i'm not sure
maybe that's maybe that's not being fair
to the people who wrote a 60-page guide
for philosophers but i think if we're
going to look at the the foundational
things
they're going to be able to tell whether
or not we're actually
doing and using active inference
i would think that at minimum those four
things are going to be present
starting with the filtering thing
because again if it's not a minimum of
two
i think we over reduce
we put a frame around it but we don't
actually know what's actually a gradient
descent and dynamically stable within
that
so
just something to think about if we're
going to write guides
thanks dean okay steven specifically on
that and then we'll go on
yeah um
just referring to this idea of screens
and it comes back to the idea of
screening off or filtering or i think
that
the x and the z here
there's a question we often in this
particular
context
they are talking a lot about screening
it off and it seems to be
whereas in other contexts say actual
constants work i feel like it's trying
to extract as much as possible from
[Music]
the the informational potential in an
environment and i think that's important
there's
is there's a very different i've i've
worked i actually used to work
as a print
uh
broker so i actually fire up these
big presses and it takes a hund a
thousand copies to get the magazine
actually starting to print properly like
the rollers and the blanket has to get
inked up and everything you've got all
this waste eventually you actually get
something that looks good and now it's
running so you've got a thousand wasted
copies basically you're trying to
extract as much as possible
from the inked up
prince print head print cylinder right
this is on a big press
now in that case then you're trying to
get as much information
basically across into the paper
now there's other cases though you can
imagine where
it's i don't know someone's taking a
video in a and there's bright lights
going on and there's you know you're
trying to filter out like we say you've
got bright light you know you're looking
at the sun you've got to filter out to
see anything
in that case you're still trying to get
your sensory data in you're still trying
to work on the action policies
but both x and z
in a traditional blanket
is a dead thing you know but how much is
x and z
um
you know
how much is that a living
kind of process at certain times that is
moving i mean you could say it's doing a
bit of everything but how much is it
trying to to to screen out noise
and
bring in and how much is it trying to
extract
you know from shannon entropy and stuff
like that so you know i thought i'd
mention that
yeah it makes me think of like being on
the phone with somebody
and it's like
you're both trying to pull as much
information out of that limited channel
and put as much into a limited channel
and so
um
let's go on to
justificatory links
between or among
dialectical categories so we'll do some
slide play
we have three
types of claims
dave i hope i'm using the word
appropriately that there are domains of
claims
mathematical
red
empirical
blue
general
green
okay
so
no um
commitments
but can somebody just like give a
specific
concise example
of where we see
one of these cross category
statements
it can be in any direction amongst the
three where is a case where somebody
uses a mathematical the first part of
their sentence is mathematical and then
the second part is empirical or vice
versa where's the situation where the
first part of someone's sentence is
mathematical and the second part is
general
so
i'm sure that many have been said even
today but let's try to get a few really
specific examples so that people can
just learn to identify these kinds of
sentences and then we'll be evaluating
what they mean so blue go for it
so nothing that's been mentioned today
but um you know the
the p-value of 0.05
you know demonstrates that that
whatever my claim is in my experiment is
significantly so that's something that's
all the time um you see the statistical
um
you know
justifying the empirical and less so i
think we're coming away from the
significance of the p-value um in
scientific literature but you see that a
lot so where would we put that kind of
where would we put statistics what
domains does statistics
jump
among
so statistics to me is math like
statistics is the sentence that bridges
that's the field that bridges
mathematics and empirical claims like so
when you make the sentence my p-value of
0.05 p less than 0.05 demonstrates that
whatever my claim is my empirical claim
is significant so for me statistics is
that bridge between math and empirical
claims awesome
yes totally agreed
we
looked at these two categories of ant
and we saw this one doing it six times
this one did it two times
we did some math on the numbers six and
two you can't do math on the ant
you do math on the numbers six and two
and from that mathematical claim
we're going to say something about those
two categories of ants so yes
mathematics going to empirical
is a lot like statistics
okay
um
what about
empirical going back to mathematics
what is a specific
natural language expression
where
somebody begins
where the warrant of the rhetoric
is empirically driven
meaning based upon observation
and then
the consequence
of the argument is mathematical
how about
because
the organism is maintaining body
temperature homeostasis
empirical
it is the case
that it is doing
predictive processing
or active inference
so here
um it's
now
there's there's so many ways to even
enter here but this would be like from
results
that's the hallmark of starting in
empirical
is you're starting with something
that is almost either trivial or just
simply a fact or observation about the
world
so from results
to
what
um
some sort of
statement about
now what's interesting about the way
that the authors did it here
is they have no
none of the three cases
have mathematics
in the second position
and that's kind of like the xkcd comic
where mathematics is like oh i'm way
over here i can't hear you the field's
arranged by purity meme
because mathematics is almost
framed as like internally coherent
and then information comes out of
mathematics
but because it's theoretical or abstract
there is an internal logic in
mathematics called proof
and then there's very little need to
have something enter mathematics
which is why it's a
we'll see as we start to flesh out this
um
shape
stephen
yeah as you're doing that i'm curious
what you think about something like
gambling so someone is
you know betting on horses it's the
statistics of the horse
gambling
and then there's their motivation for
gambling so in terms of the empirical
you can see okay the behavior
is fairly consistent certainly over
a type of gambler at horse race the math
can be established but then there's i
don't know whether it goes into the
general well what's people's motivation
for
the teleology but maybe i'm jumping the
gun there but am i on the right lines
there
in terms of how would you put that into
this um
scenario
can you restate it with an antecedent
and a postseason just a specific
rhetorical nucleus
okay so there's um
because x then why oh because
because
there is a
group of people
at
a horse
racing track
and
because we know that these horses
have performed
in a certain way over previous races
we can predict the probability
that the horse will
win
or be
told to people to win as being x
the motivation for people to make that
influence about
and the behavioral choices
is maybe more general
but that seems to yes
we'll get to the general edge because
it's very connected to math okay dean
no i'm just going to say i i like the
word results there but i
i think what
what it's implied is is that there were
a certain number of observations taken
that then moved the formalism
to something specific
is that
am i just confirming something or am i
putting more in there that needs than
needs to be
i had a really similar question um
so um when you're talking about going
from empirical to math
to me like you brought up um
the the idea of like a probability
density or like a non-equilibrium steady
state and like that's immediately what
came to my mind so i don't know if if
that's echoes what dean just said it
does
let's get at the distinction between
general claims and mathematical claims
so
math is sometimes seen as general
and when ideas are framed mathematically
indeed there's a lot of overlap but the
authors do separate it out it's in
section 4.2.2
so
what would be like an example
of going from a mathematical
to a general because math
then general or
because general claim then mathematics
well you can you can talk about the rate
of the rate of the rate of acceleration
due to gravity
and then then make the general claim
that
that uh
if i if i go from
from this height to this height
um
i can i can expect to
hit the ground at a certain rate of
speed or something i would imagine
okay
great i'm going to also pull out just
two examples from
yeah from the paper so here we go so
we're in 4.2.2 so there's gonna be two
examples given
so again we're looking here at math
going to general
and then we'll see if we can run it back
so how can mathematical claims justify
general claims
ramstead at all 2018 assert
the fep is a mathematical formulation
that explains from first principles the
characteristics of biological systems
that are able to resist
decay and persist over time
first part of the sentence mathematical
second part general
it rests on the idea that all biological
systems instantiate
a hierarchy
a hierarchical generative model of the
world that implicitly minimizes its
entropy by minimizing free energy
i almost see the reflection in that
sentence
um
that because of the hierarchical
generative model
which is a general claim
though a formal one
then
there is a mathematical implication
so maybe we can put this ramstead 2018
here
okay and then here's the second or a
second example that the author is raised
in the paper
axel constance contribution to this
topical collection
uses a mathematical claim to make a
general claim
on the basis of a numerical example
he argues against the claim that
minimizing free energy entails life
rather he believes the converse is true
life entails minimizing free energy
we read and loved that paper and that's
very much related to the um
quote like one
ugly fact destroys a beautiful theory or
something like that
um
now is an example
mathematical or empirical
mat if it were just on the basis of a
family of equations
he argues against the general claim
but then again isn't even the family of
an equations
an empirical
observation from the domain of math but
we'll put it in the section that they
had it
so in these cases we're using specific
math examples and that was sort of the
provocation of
and axel's paper
which was like i did a math example so
that's kind of resting on both the
empirical and the mathematical i did a
math example
and now i'm going to make a claim about
a general
topic which is the relationship between
free energy minimization and life
so that is certainly
moving in this direction
whereas um so
because math can be abstracted and
generalized
there's often similarity here
because
math
rests upon specific examples
even if the examples are
some examples are more general than
other examples
it still can be said that they're
empirical
not exactly in the way that cat location
measurement is but still
it is the case that
math produces results there can be a
result section in a math paper
what about this third edge
what's the relationship between general
and empirical
and let's leave math out of it
blue
so this is something like um
i i think about like what dean was
saying
because
acceleration to due to gravity is you
know negative 9.8 meters per second
squared
uh when i drop this apple it will fall
to the ground
like that goes maybe empirical to
general
when i when i drop the apple
um because when i drop the apple it
falls to the ground
comma
gravity exists in the whole universe
that was
quite a jump
well because apples
fell in not down
that's flat earth
because apples fell in
gravity
is everywhere
okay that's one example
so then i was thinking of like a sort of
ant evolution example so the general to
empirical would be like because of the
way that evolution by natural selection
is
um
ants
optimize
task efficiency
and then
the other direction
would be like
because in my experiment 30 percent of
the time
ants were observed to be doing this
selection has been acting on ants
so
these are very interesting because are
there some edges that we rest upon more
like what if we could just number these
edges one two three four five six
and then annotate
and people could have different
perspectives on it but we could annotate
papers
in different areas and okay
if you're just doing one one one one one
one one one
it's like a one note paper from a
structural rhetorical perspective
under what situations is that
preferable not preferable
are there certain edges that are weak
are there pairs of edges like a cord
that we want to play together
just like the ramstead it was like sort
of forwards and backwards
law of the jungle law of the pack
from the mathematics to the general
and then instantly
a grammatical reflection
from the empirical
into the mathematical
um okay uh stephen then dean
um
one question first just ask empirical
could be seen as is that exact base
empirical means observed
observed so the exact base if you're
just taking however you lay that out
it hasn't been computed
beyond
observed okay so effectively that's true
okay that's the first thing and then
general
in most senses is what we might call
inflated or higher dimensional
so we would go generally speaking the
models are empirical
from observe observations into math into
generative model into some general
pattern of action selection
however
it could be possible
but
generally it's intractable
for complex situations to go from
general
to empirical
and then try and get the math out
which is kind of what alex is saying is
like
there's a general principle
that empirically plays out
but good luck finding the map to show it
outside of a bacteria
okay dean
so i find it an interesting daniel that
you
just just to keep the conversation
sort of alive as you talked about the
edges of those three circles
and i think
i think the the task of being able to
find examples
of those bi-directionalities
again goes back to that question of so
so what are the rules
and how fluid are they and as we're
moving from one node
so there's a change the moving from node
to node we're building that relationship
we're building out these rules
is that
is that one of the great byproducts
of being able to
maneuver and manipulate not getting
stuck with only
a sense of unidirectionality
or oneness is if does this reinforce the
idea that if we're going to actually
really be able to demonstrate the use of
active inference for example as a
instrument or a tool to be able to gain
a greater awareness
are we really then
talking about how we
not just find examples of rules but
actually form them
because that's what you did that was the
exercise that you just went you just
built a whole bunch of rules i know you
i know we've laid them down on the slide
as examples but
that those relationships
now are they're not even bridged right
there
they've now got some sort of a a pairing
effect
so is that was that is that is that it
i'm looking today
back to the and then what happens what
i'm looking today for is so we got our
way we got our way to what is there is
there now an awareness a sense
that we didn't have before
we went through that that effort
and these and it's the thing that kicks
out
rules or is it just examples what do you
think
i'm asking you daniel because you you
did the most of this
work do you see the rules or do we just
see the examples
i just think about how in a nested
cognitive model
the outcome of one layer is like the
inflow of another layer so even a rule
can be a rule in one
layer or application but yet it's also
an example
of a rule
mathematics and general claims
tend to be more
rule-like
but again even rules are examples
whereas empirical
it's always the exception that proves
the rule like it's the exception is the
observation which transcends rules
because if it happened it had to have
occurred
and so the empirical
to me is like examples
when you're in this domain
and then
movement
away from the examples
in the scientific empirical sense
pushes us into the rule
world
so here
this red line
is going to be
more example like
and so in that sense like
in pure
with the caveat again that even rules
and generalizations are examples of
but in the
scientific empirical sense this is more
like an example
can you hear can you hear in your own
explanation the sort of justifactory
link
between example and rule
do you hear yourself justifying the
difference between how we might
look at math in general as being
different than the empirical that's all
i'm trying to bring out and and again
it's it's a not
it's not it's not it's there's nothing
it mean it makes perfect sense
but i think if we're going to find
if we're going to find
that somebody used a guide
and what is the what is the
what is the result of that it's going to
be that people have a better
sense of
what the rules are
and what the examples are and what the
relationship is between those two things
that would be
goodness gracious i mean if i'm talking
to anybody between the ages of
22 and 62 if we could get there holy
mackerel
thanks steven in terms of in terms of
opening up our understanding of things
right
one thing i think with what you're
saying there dean is um
which is because it does become
interesting and
something daniel mentioned
when we have multi-scale
the actual nature
of the rule example
actually can shift
and there's teleology shift that that i
think is kind of revolutionary in a way
when we start to think about
there's a variation
in the nature of what rules are present
you know
so you know the sort of rules around
what it means for me to do something in
my environment
um
myself individually i can't play that
game
my organs can't play that game
individually right so
um there's these
there's there's there is um
this this challenge right of integration
or maybe this is ideal okay well
as well as saying
what's happening
um
what where is something or what temple
an imperial a temple and um
temple and spatial scale
does it hold
and i think that maybe
something that's kind of interesting is
where
so generally speaking people go to the
racetrack
and you know they behave in certain
behaviors at the scale of
um their their their part in society
but they um
and we have empirical data to support
that
however
um at the biological level
um it may be something to do with um
adrenaline rush you could talk about or
you could talk about
the fact that they just happen to have
nice sandwich bar and someone enjoys
getting the food right they don't even
like gambling that much um whatever it
is or wearing a funny hat to ascot so
there's there's there's something
there that could
how do we i wonder that
that that multi-scale question
because i'm very caught with the idea
that you've got axel constant taking
very very
small
you have this incredibly small
world being addressed with active
inference and then we have quite
sort of
you could say gross
examples at scale which
ends up revealing a lot
you know at larger scale um
but uh
i wonder what you think daniel about how
what what
happens and that that reflects what
daniel i think was saying about nested
systems and
they're sort of informing each other in
a way like
if i if i think i'm gonna
win some money on the races and i better
get myself sorted i might sustain my
stomach a bit more so i've got a better
glucose level to make a good choice
right so suddenly
there's two different levels coming into
play or just different scales so
i don't know if that's i don't think
that confusing things but i think it
does make the modeling question
because active influence is ultimately a
modeling process
um
which
is trying to get at
i would say it's trying to either get at
the general
or to
to
predict an empirical
if i if i'm looking at this diagram but
maybe i'm i'm mistaken there
right where is active inference
in this is this the trace of active
inference
is this the map and then we play on this
territory
what is the adjacent possible and
so we can ask first where's active
inference here
and when is it here and then
what next dean
yeah this is where i think it's it's
about it's in the relationships
and how we decide to parse those
relationships and it seems rather
arbitrary and i think it's one of the
reasons why we're
we can always disagree on when the rules
are in effect and when they're not in
effect i mean it's happening up here in
canada we've got all these rules in
place and then
people just
decide to pull up big trucks to the
border and go no we don't like your rule
right and so now there's
being canadian now we have to figure out
how we're going to deal with that
because
we don't have any guns so i guess we're
going to have to
disassemble all the trucks or something
by hand but the thing is is that
if if you actually look at this active
inferences in the relationship
and i think it's and then and i think
to steven's point
if if we if we think that a rule applies
without limits
that's the scale free part of it there
from a mathematical standpoint we can we
can find cases where that's true but
then there's a very scale friendly part
of it which says i don't like this rule
doesn't seem to make sense in this
specific situation and that's where axel
came forward
he essentially said i'm sorry but
and and so did um i'm sorry the uh
there was another author we had very
recently who
who agreed and said there's it was majid
rajid said look there's there's a piece
to this that says
there's something that's local and
proximal and specific and
why are we pretending like that that
fits the same
context as scale free so
again i think
i don't see that means that active
inference is useless i think what it
means is it can tell us when we can
differentiate and when we can integrate
that's relational
so one thing this made me think of is
that
reading a paper on
free energy free energy principle active
inference
look at the road map
there's no
dialectic
within
a domain
the claims are listed but it goes
immediately to the relationship so it's
like minimum two domains okay
now
it makes me think about the structure of
scientific communication so in the
results section of the paper well so the
introduction
might have a lot of general and
empirical claims
selection acts on ants and look at their
mandibles and we know this about niche
construction and look at how they do it
so that is like a very introductory
piece there's not often formalisms in
the introduction of the paper so that
sort of blue arrow general and empirical
is very introductory in its scope
then the results section of the paper
is like blue mentioned it's about like
empirical and math we saw it do it 11
times and here's the p value and then we
did this and we calculated the model and
so it's like it shouldn't generalize in
some senses
and then in the discussion
there's probably all edges in play
but especially math to general
because it's now been generalized beyond
the mere empirical because we saw a
p-value in the difference between the
nest mates of this type and that type it
does say something about evolution or
because there's something happening at
an evolutionary time scale it's
consistent or inconsistent with our
mathematical summary statistics yes that
came from empirical but that edge is
more in play dean
and then
in simple simple terms that's how and
when we fit phit the rule
and that almost
it does return us to the third p
um
but i think it's um so we'll kind of
close this
section on the
2.4 whatever it was with the uh links
amongst the dialectical categories
active inference as a trans discipline
all of these are often in play and it's
almost like
if
the paper would have just been
lists of empirical observations there'd
be nothing contentious because it
wouldn't make any general claims that
would just be called a data set
if it were just
general claims
it would be just philosophy
and
that's not to say philosophy is easier
or simpler it's like it doesn't trigger
anyone's
domain crossing alarm
but like mathematical biology that does
raise people's alarms or generalizing
from math you're saying that because of
the free energy minimizing that there's
a general imperative for information
foraging
or
relationship between the general and the
empirical of course always fraught in
empirical science okay you measured in
that laboratory study with those
undergrads and that stimuli and you're
going to say something about aggression
so
it's just very interesting because
active inference does lay
claim or at least
lay play
to all these areas
that
it raises alarms
on all sides
but how do we take that alarm pheromone
and attention
and then
just
align it with something that's going to
be a public good
rather than just
let it fizzle stephen
that's very helpful and the nature of
action
and the idea of a tediology
as soon as that comes in i don't know if
you can avoid being in in the general
now maybe active vision that's just
doing
a thousand dimensional interpretation of
a data set you know
can stick with empirical math you know
it's either recognizing a photo it's not
recognizing a photo doing some deep
deep computational processes but
action
and particularly then action policy and
then tediology
um
and would you say that would you say
does does general claims or is where
would teleology fit in here
[Music]
teleology is never directly measured
is that fair to say
so it can
it can alway it can be it can be in
green
but it cannot be blue one can say i
observed sorry blue
but i chose the colors for a reason too
one could observe
the animal trying to swim to the surface
and you can say well the teleology is
obviously not to drown or something like
that but that's actually structured as
because i empirically observed the
swimming behavior
i am going to make a claim about the
teleology
so
um
i would say teleology is in a general
case
even another
spin on this one
would be
empirical is like x
this is the data that we're actually
observing
in general
is unobserved you can't observe
things that are general you're only
observing what blake calls the minute
particulars
w
what is math
math is
in the examples that we looked at
it's like the process
oh wait active inference it's a
mathematical process theory
so math is a process or of inference
that yes
connects to generalities
and this is not hard and fast i hope is
not being interpreted in the most
rigorous way
but
it does generalize
because it has to be
like the intermediating blanket so let's
pull
this w and x back in here
all right so
here we have the empirical states here
being observed that's our data
okay
then here's the things that we would
like to generalize on
and then
this gets to dean's question about how
do you go from this to equations
and here's math as our sort of blanket
in the middle
that's when we actually do whether it's
variational
uh
base
or whether it's exact or whether there's
some other mathematical approach
it's how we're gonna go from
these generalized or hypothesized things
that we didn't observe
how are we going to connect that domain
and so it's almost like a little
boomerang
so
there's probably a lot more to explore
here too dean
i just like how i like how this has come
together because
math as we said well as i mentioned
before i think in the authors in the
author's mind the motivation moving
forward on the paper was math could be a
vehicle
and it can move the process along
because it is a process or it can be an
impediment the other thing that's really
interesting here is because it's in the
middle
isn't math got a lot of rules in it i
mean come on
right so
again i don't think i don't think we're
contradicting ourselves i just think
we're asking so again what do we allow
to pass through the sieve
and what do we hold back
and then what assumptions do we make
about the sophistication
what what's the minimum amount of
sophistication around the math process
that one must have dr carl fristen said
you must have you must have a good
grounded sense of what the math is if
you're going to go forward like he
didn't couch his words
he said if you want this to become a
vehicle and not an impediment you're
gonna have to get familiar with the mat
so
and sometimes oh the math is not the
territory you know important
contribution and memes for sure
if the debate were about
whether territories were maps it would
be the silver bullet to simply claim
that the math is not the territory but
it's like right and we want the map
so that we can take action and be on our
road trip or whatever
so
it's
the math is not the territory while it's
the conclusion
or the
um
second part of the rhetoric
for some
especially philosophers who might be
interested in what is really out there
because the math is not the territory
comma then what
that's like
the dot two of active
which is
instead of just debating well yeah well
because of homeostasis what can you
really say about teleology and because
of allostasis does that contribute to a
new understanding of niche construction
they're all important questions
but then
where do we go
when we put the math is not the
territory as our antecedent rather than
our conclusion rhetorically stephen
yeah and like when you put here so
first the math i totally agree i was
thinking that vehicle was thinking it
also
takes a different so for instance say i
have a million dollars
it gets picked up it's counted it's
picked up in a car taken somewhere and
then it's counted as a million dollars
the bit in between it's not math it's
just stuff right
but in this process theory
it's the in a way in the mod it's the
math it's enabling and it could be an
entropic
process you know it could be math in
these
maybe some sort of virtual numbers way
or noise way but the math is the vehicle
for the data
right there is no data there is no
banknote right there is only a process
which enables
the general to the empirical and the
empirical in this context is a
is a modeled empirical
in a way what we're saying is we're
going to take most of the models that we
see there's a very simple general idea
about behavior say ryan smith's idea
about how the heart behaves how the gut
behaves
something about how
access consciousness or actually access
awareness is achieved
some general
thing and then we basically do what we
might call it a modeled empirical but
you could flip it around the other way
and you could have
um okay well the real world
we could have
a high dimensional empirical outside
there
what's the general w what's the general
x
internally what's the general
which is what we use as our heuristics
you know
um which could be kind of interesting as
well which is maybe more
in the action because this is coming in
on the um
century right but uh i think this is
quite helpful would you say that's true
it's a modeled empirical what we get on
the
in terms of how we work with it in the
active inference
i mean looking back
on it is there anyone who disagrees that
empirical is always as modeled
like
it's kind of funny like
now i want to put a little red guy
always intervening
on this edge
little blue guy
always talking about specific examples
of math and generality
and then
you know the generalization is we use
the the um you know in equal variance
t-test
so we generalized
to connect the empirical and the math
dean
i i really didn't want to go there here
but i have to i was way too excited last
week when i had a little thought bubble
and said wouldn't it be cool if
my if michael
or sorry if stephen mann and connor
hines if we could get them in a room and
instead of them talking about what they
know
get them to go through this process
because that's essentially what we want
to do is is we want to have that little
guy
pop out as opposed to the one who knows
so much in a dense way about their math
or so much in a dense way about their
philosophical guide
because that's when that's when the true
grasp of what the potential is and it's
not it's not about always having the
right answer it's coming up with the
with the best answer in that moment
right and if we could get more of those
kind of situations
i think people would actually
i think people actually come away
feeling even more confident because
that's what this is about
it's about confidence developing i think
one thought on that is like
it's possible to stay purely
internal to math and that's the internal
logic of proofs
it's also possible to stay internal to
general claims
and do philosophy
is it possible to stay purely
within the realm of empiricism
in the trivial case yes if you're just
aggregating data sets and never
interpreting them
yes
but empirical
in
application must either connect to a
general question like you know again we
observe the ants and now we're going to
talk about evolution so that's still
qualitative
but it's it's an edge and then
it rests on math when it's more
statistical and on generalities when
it's more um
[Music]
conceptual
but it's just sort of interesting that
the the internal logic of empiricism is
basically just data integrity
but it's like
pre-interpretation which is perfect for
it being x
whereas there's a whole
guild structure and discipline
around internal mathematics and internal
generalizations and philosophy
and so it's like
i and i also really agree with that
having them i thought you're gonna say
just get in the same room and then just
talk about food or music or something
like that no but i i know what you mean
have them and just like
we're all learning by doing in this
space
and to say that this is a lifelong
journey would just be a total
understatement it's
it's broader and deeper than that
so
how do we recognize the complexity of
this
arrangement as well as the adjacent
possibles are the ways that it could
have been made other end states that we
could have reached
bringing in any number of fourth points
to make a tetrahedra
any other number of orders of paths that
we could have done to reach this point
like if we had started with these little
dots
and then later added the arrows
and
how did we start this whole thing with
examples of each edge
so
getting to the super like fractal
multi-scale level where
and we didn't even add any formalisms or
mathematics here
but we could have done some pseudo code
or some pseudo equations
to really start to link this and to lean
more on our mathematical leg and that's
the whole thing that you just said about
confidence dean which is like
this is the space that we're going to be
bouncing around and you can ignore
statistics and you can just
have an emotional response to p-values
and stuff like that but
you will need that as part of the
journey
um
we can't just be like the post office
vehicles that don't make left turns
we have to make all of our tools
available
at the team level
and then trust that with like
distributed cognition and with
guides and
wayfinders and peer facilitation
that like
we can
make it work
despite
how vast this area is
so
yes
steven as we go for our final commentary
yeah i think you made a good point there
um with that green arrow just one last
thing with the green arrow you put there
could that be um more implemented
implementable
um
like it's becomes more implementable as
you go that direction um away from the
math
uh with a mixture of general and
empirical uh just curious
so the arrows
yeah the arrows i mean again they're
open to interpretation in other ways it
could have been done i was thinking what
links up math and empirical they're both
more numerical
that's the bottom edge okay then then um
what
then what makes math in general similar
they're less example-like
and then what is the similarity between
empirical and general so what is not
just pointing what's the arrow that
doesn't point too general
what's the arrow that points between
general and empirical
and what distinguishes mathematics
from general empirical it might be its
formalism but
general
is it
well i'm thinking implementation or
maybe this does get into teleology like
it shows you more like the empiricals
what's actually happened so like like i
always this is an example is the um the
accountant said to us once it always
stuck in my mind is you know i've said
this before
what is an organization doing what's
there about he said don't tell me your
mission don't tell me your vision show
me your budget
show me what you're doing or show me
where you spend your time
so
in a way it's like that what's the
empirical as well as the
uh that goes to the general to show me
well that's that gives an idea then
of something that can be done
as opposed to
words or even a mathematical well words
can be like a mathematical formula
in many ways that help
tell people what you want them to think
but maybe not what is going on so anyway
i like those three arrows i think it's
pretty useful
any final comments in the last one
minute
dean and then blue
so real quickly i think that a lot of
times conferences people go and they
want to talk about what they know
but i think that this example today
was an example of where you come in not
necessarily knowing but discovering
i think it's another fine example of
what we're talking about when we're
talking about active inference
if i caught
stephen mann and conor in the same room
the place that i would want to begin is
what what don't you know how would you
guys attack this from not your strength
preferences probabilities and fit but
from what you what you don't know but is
still in the room
and i think that's very complementary to
the to the more traditional conference
way of disseminating information there's
my word for today
and then even socially at the conference
people connect with the people who they
do know
and that's the little click network
instead of connecting with people who we
don't know and so it also ties
to hopefully some of our values too so
blue any last thoughts
just
i'm just thought of complexity science
and the interdisciplinarity and um the
real value that goes into co-learning or
working
outside of your comfort zone because
really like that's where where the
growth happens
so i like those ideas a lot
yep working with people you know
can have amazing pragmatic utility
and it must be balanced with the
epistemic and with expanding our
horizons and perspectives as well so
yeah totally agreed
well
another fun one
can't say we prepared too much but i
think in the end it went just fine
so
thank you all for joining and for
participating and we'll